<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Capt. Badiley's reply to certaine declarations from Capt. Seamen, Cap. Ell, &amp; Cap. Fisher as he found them divulged abroad in a fallacious pamphlet, called The remonstrance of the fight neer Legorn, between the English and the Dutch. : As also many other particulars, as they were presented to his Excellency the Lord General Cromwell, and the Right Honourable, the Councell of State.</title>
            <author>Badiley, Richard, d. 1657.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77159</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B388</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R225715</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">43077468</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 43077468</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151526</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77159)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151526)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2263:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Capt. Badiley's reply to certaine declarations from Capt. Seamen, Cap. Ell, &amp; Cap. Fisher as he found them divulged abroad in a fallacious pamphlet, called The remonstrance of the fight neer Legorn, between the English and the Dutch. : As also many other particulars, as they were presented to his Excellency the Lord General Cromwell, and the Right Honourable, the Councell of State.</title>
                  <author>Badiley, Richard, d. 1657.</author>
                  <author>Cromwell, Oliver, 1599-1658.</author>
                  <author>Appleton, Henry, fl. 1650-1654.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 24, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Matthew Simmons, in Aldersgate-streete,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: William Andrews Clark Memorial Library, University of California, Los Angeles, California.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Anglo-Dutch War, 1652-1654 --  Pamphlets.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151526:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CAPT. BADILEY'S REPLY <hi>TO CERTAINE</hi> DECLARATIONS FROM Capt. <hi>Seamen,</hi> Cap. <hi>Ell,</hi> &amp; Cap. <hi>Fiſher. AS HE</hi> Found them divulged abroad in a Fallacious PAMPHLET, called <hi>The Remonſtrance of the Fight neer</hi> Legorn, <hi>between the Engliſh and the Dutch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AS ALSO: Many other Particulars, as they were preſented to his Excellency the Lord Generall CROMWELL, And the Right Honourable, the Councell of State.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Matthew Simmons,</hi> in <hi>Alderſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate-ſtreete,</hi> 1653.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb facs="tcp:151526:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:151526:2"/>
            <head>THE ANSWER <hi>TO</hi> CAPT. SEAMANS DECLARATION.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt he ſaith, when Captain <hi>Cox</hi> was ſent to know in what a condition they were in, then he replyed, ſo and ſo.</p>
            <p>To that paſſage I anſwer thus, having receiv'd about 20 Letters from <hi>Legorn,</hi> acquainting me with the ſtubborneſſe and averſneſſe of the ſaid <hi>Seaman,</hi> to doe any ſervice that might have conduced as much to their Employers benefit, and their owne goods, as to the honour of the Nation, and having been ſufficiently advis'd of the backwardneſſe of the States ſervants, I ſent the afore-named Capt. <hi>Coxe</hi> to put ſome life into them, by giving them to underſtand how much it concerned them, for ends before denoted, to act vigorouſly, and come away to my Aſſiſtance, but nothing would, faire meanes, or acts of Civility, work (in the leaſt) upon the ſaid <hi>Seaman,</hi> but the production of ſome ſuch ſcorne as was ordinary with him; <hi>What, doe you thinke we come hither to convey the States
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:151526:3"/>Ships? Cannot they be gone of themſelves, without the helpe of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants Ships?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the next place he ſaith, <hi>As ſoone as the States Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners came, he rendred obedience unto them;</hi> which is a deſperate untruth; For being at <hi>Legorn</hi> the beginning of <hi>Nov.</hi> with all the Arguments I could uſe in a friendly and perſwaſive way, I could not prevaile with him, and Capt. <hi>Roope,</hi> and thereby they hindred Capt. <hi>Marſh,</hi> who told me he would readily ſubmit to ſerve the State, if the reſt would embrace the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions, and ſerve.</p>
            <p>However a good while afterwards (whil'ſt) I was abſent at <hi>Porto Longone,</hi> Mr. <hi>Longland</hi> carried the States Commiſſions on bord their Ships, and reading of it at their Main-maſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Witneſſe, prevailed with them to land their Goods, and ſerve the State; whereas, had they readily imbrac't the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions, we might have been in a far better Capacity then we were.</p>
            <p>Next, he tels a peece of ridiculous ſtuffe, that at <hi>Legorn in the afternoone</hi> (we may gueſſe when) <hi>a Counſell was call'd, and he was told but ſo and ſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here he playes the <hi>Weaver,</hi> and mingles a great many falſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties together: He ſaith, Mr. <hi>Longland and myſelfe told him we muſt be gone in fifteene dayes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To that I anſwer: Truth is, I did acquaint him the great Duke would thruſt us out of his Port, and in twelve dayes we muſt be gone, elſe for ought I could perceive, we muſt be deſtroyed, more Guns being then brought downe, and plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt the <hi>Leopard;</hi> and he well knoweth, I went on bord the <hi>Sampſon,</hi> as well as on bord other Ships, and caus'd all his Officers and Marriners to be cal'd together, and being aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled, I made a Speech among them to this effect, <hi>Our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition is much like the Leapers we read of,</hi> or <hi>like to thoſe that have had enemies before and behind them;</hi> and the riſe I took from thence, to deſire they might quit themſelves like Engliſh men, when ever they came to it, is not unknowne to him, except he ſtopt his eares all the time I was ſpeaking.</p>
            <p>But in the next place, after he had ſhewed himſelfe liker a Mouſe then a Man that flood up for the Honour of his owne
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:151526:3"/>Nation, he turnes Champion for the Great Duke, and as one that had con'd his Letter at that Court, ſaid, that <hi>he heard we might have ſtayed ten dayes, and ten dayes after that, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to that paſſage I anſwer, the more unworthy perſon he, that he ſhould never acquaint me with any ſuch thing; for I underſtood neither directly, nor indirectly, but that we muſt have been deſtroyed in the Great Dukes Port, if we had ſtayed longer then our limited time.</p>
            <p>The next thing that concernes me to Anſwer, is, that Cap. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pcher</hi> told him they were <hi>neere the Lanthorne in the night, but in the morning we were two or three leagues off.</hi> Indeed we were neere the Lanthorne within four or five miles thereof, about midnight, and if then he had not laine like a <hi>Lurdaine</hi> upon the Bed or Couch, but had vigorouſly endeavoured to have put my Order in execution, when I ſent for him among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, I believ'ſt he had ſav'd his Ship, and the State had ſav'd their Repute they loſt in ſome meaſure, by employing as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, ſuch Paltry Drones.</p>
            <p>But ſaith he, <hi>In the morning we were three or foure leagues off:</hi> For Anſwer, I leave it to underſtanding Sea-men to judge (how far we were off) having all the night long not above fourteen or fifteen fathome water, and ſince we ſaw not the <hi>Malora</hi> before night, we could not tell aſſuredly whether we were to the ſouthward, or to the eaſtward of him, untill it grew the lighter for day, and then we haſtned in as the wind gave leave, with all the ſaile we could make.</p>
            <p>Next, he tels you, <hi>That my Lievtenant was ſent in to them to call them out, and that upon their lives, before I was too much inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</hi> Mark now, if the Queſtion were asked this impudent perſon, being it was on your lives, <hi>what will become of your life now?</hi> ſince it can be proved notwithſtanding that Order, you lay like a Drone four or five houres after, and did nothing at all as to going out.</p>
            <p>If he Object, <hi>We were to be engaged firſt;</hi> (I know that was agreed on, if the Ships did not come out in the night) but ſince he ſtaid while it was day, why ſtaid he not untill we were engaged? himſelfe ſaith, <hi>They ſhould come out before we were too much engaged,</hi> Ergo, They ſhould have ſtayed in the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:151526:4"/>day time untill wee had beene Engaged.</p>
            <p>But to mend the matter, <hi>He thought I would not Engage.</hi> This is pretty ſtuffe; but if it opens not a gap for every inferiour Officer to take hold of his Commanders Throat, I ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine ſatisfied to lye under that indignity for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</p>
            <p>In the next place, he tells us that <hi>Mr. Longland and others ordered them to goe out next morning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For Anſwer, pray let every one judge, who is like to ſpeak truth. Mr. <hi>Longland</hi> writes in ſundry Letters to ſeveral men, and to my ſelfe, that when he heard they were gone out be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I had engaged, he ſhut himſelfe into his Chamber, and in his thoughts gave all for loſt.</p>
            <p>In the next place, Here's Oath made by a credible witneſſe, that Capt. <hi>John Wood,</hi> who loſt both his ſhip and life in the buſineſſe, confeſſed when he was going out of the world, that <hi>their deſtruction was of themſelves by going out too ſoon in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, it being againſt the reſult of their owne deliberate Counſell of War, and diametrically croſſe to what was concluded among our part of the Fleet,</hi> as may be ſeen among the Copies of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, dated the 1 or 11 of <hi>March,</hi> in the cloſe there was this concluded on; That if the Enemy come out, and the wind were Eaſterly, we ſhould toyle them off by ſtanding a little to the ſouthward. Compare that with my Letter of the 3 or 13 of <hi>March</hi> at 4 a Clock in the morning, and there I told told them (as I remember) (and Capt. <hi>Appleton</hi> confeſſeth as much by his Letter of that dayes date, at foure in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone) <hi>I was very loath to hazard that Squadron, being ſomewhat the leſſe, wherefore I would not have them venture before they ſaw me engaged:</hi> or words to that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Next he ſaith, <hi>That when I ſaw them out of the Mould, I tackt about.</hi> To which I anſwer, for ends before denoted, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in regard it was the opinion of Mr. and Pilots, that we could not weather the <hi>Malora,</hi> we did tack off for halfe an houre, the head-moſt of the <hi>Flemiſh</hi> Fleet then bearing away directly with us, and had been with us in halfe an houre, if our Ships in the Mould had not impudently come out as they did: And I appeale unto all underſtanding Seaman in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:151526:4"/>
               <hi>England</hi> (that knows what <hi>Legorn</hi>-Road is) whether it be not moſt hazardous to engage with ſuch Ships of Charge, as we had in that Auger-hole: And whether we were not as gallantly to paſſe as any men in the world could be, to goe jameing off with our Main-ſaile hal'd up, (as well to clear our Ordnance in the Capſtain Way, as otherwiſe) ſince the <hi>Malora</hi> did now beare N. N. E. about a mile off; for (if they had ſtaid a little longer in the Mould) we had Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>room enough: and as I ſaid to them that were next to mee, <hi>Now if haife a dozen of theſe fellowes of Van Gallens Crew comes on board, the Parragons ſide will hold them, and by that time eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one hath had his ſhare, and that wee are all hot at our buſineſſe, &amp; then the Ships in the Mould will out, and coming freſh on the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie, I doubt not but by Gods aſſiſtance we ſhall have the day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet as ſoon as we ſaw the ſhips in the Mould coming out, and that the Enemie tack'd upon them, we ſet our Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile, and top-gallant-ſailes, and ſtood in with all the Saile we could make, and as the winde gave leave: This is prov'd by ſundry Witneſſes upon oath, and I dare preſume to find as many ſcore, as there are particular perſons to atteſt ſo much, that I loſt no time in coming in, and ſent Captaine <hi>Mings</hi> to tell the Commander of the Frigots, I would have them haſten in with all the Saile they could make, to help them that ſtood moſt in need of Aſſiſtance: But before I came within ſhot, the <hi>Sampſon</hi> after halfe an houres diſpute, or leſſe, not having men on the upper Deck to trim Sails, was all on a light fire. Concerning the manner of the calling off the Fleet, I have ſpoken elſe-where, and being chas'd by the eight ſhips, I ſhall ſpeak to it, when I come to anſwer <hi>Ell,</hi> and <hi>Fiſher.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But in the Cloſe he ſaith, <hi>If I had beene a Pentioner to the State of</hi> Holland, <hi>I could not have done them better ſervice then I did.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is an Expreſſion, that ſhewes the man (as we uſe to ſay of a picture that is drawn to the life) I can hardly think there is ever an Enemy I have in <hi>England,</hi> but muſt needs confeſſe it's pure malice.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:151526:5"/>
            <p> But now conſidering what I have declared in Anſwer to C. <hi>Appletons Remonſtrance,</hi> and the <hi>Affidavits</hi> that are annexed, and Letters, let the world judge who was likelieſt to be the State of <hi>Hollands</hi> Pentioner, he or I.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>In a compleat number of Particulars, every ſyllable whereof is, or will be proved upon Oath.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, if not by the open defiance he made to the State of <hi>England,</hi> as our Letters from <hi>Legorn</hi> can teſtifie; yet by the great ſtubbornneſſe, and perverſneſſe that was in him to aſſiſt in my firſt Engagement (prov'd at large) in humane reaſon occaſioned all the ruine befell us neer that place, and was the cauſe why the Merchants goods are not in <hi>England;</hi> he would not help us, and therefore God orders it out, that we ſhould not be able to help him.</p>
               <p>Secondly, His backwardneſſe above all men to goe out to Sea, and doe ſervice, when hee was the States ſervant, ſaying, <hi>To goe out upon nine or tenne of the Enemies inferiour ſhips (when wee had ſixe ſuch gallant ſhips to have engaged them, and ſo breake our way through) was to loſe three or foure good ſhips in his opinion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, If his Prayer would help on his Ruine, then I am ſure he wanted not to wiſh, with as much earneſtneſſe as a man could doe (even in my preſence) that the <hi>Sampſon</hi> were of a light fire, and that it griev'd him to look on her (in regard he had receiv'd ſome diſcontent from his men) whereupon as one aſtoniſh'd, conſidering how lately he had loſt a ſhip by fire, I replyed, <hi>Hold, hold, Captaine</hi> Seaman, <hi>of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes God annexes his Amen to ſuch paſſionate expreſſions.</hi> Add to that his running aſhoar very few dayes before his diſaſter, at a time he knows he ought to be better employ'd, <hi>viz.</hi> the Lords day (for men that were but civill could not chooſe but cry ſhame on't) to ſee his ſervants all that day act the parts of Effeminates in womens apparell. I ſay (let the world think what they will) I judge it occaſion'd God to leave him to effeminateneſſe of ſpirit, at the time when hee ſhould have ſhewed more man-hood, and therein he did the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151526:5"/>Dutch as good ſervice as if he had been their Pentioner; and he well knows, I told him then, I fear'd a hand of God was not farre from him.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, When as I ſent my Lieutenant to wiſh them to act vigorouſly, by cutting their Faſts immediately, and come out, the wind blowing afreſh off ſhoare, and we being neere the Lanthorn to receive them, according as my Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant makes Oath (as if indeed he had been Pentioner to the <hi>Dutch</hi>) he would not riſe off his Pallat to the Captains Conſultation, but there lay like a Cow, when a buſineſſe was to be tranſacted of ſo high concernment to the honour of the Nation, the ſaving of mens lives, and benefit of all our Nations Merchants in point of Trade.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, His giving conſent to come out ſo ſoone in the morning, before we had wrought in our Ships and Frigots neer the Mould-head to receive them, or were engag'd with the Enemie.</p>
               <p>Sixtly, That contrary to all reaſon and order being out, as if he had indented before-hand to be a means of the <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> deſtruction, runs with all his men under Hatches (as ſaith our Letters from <hi>Legorn:</hi>) Whereas if ſome perſons had been kept on the upper Deck to have trim'd her Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile, doubtleſſe ſhe had come away cleare of young <hi>Trumpe,</hi> and the Fireſhip alſo.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, After Mr. <hi>Longland</hi> had ſhewed favour to him and other Captaines in time of their impriſonment, by his writing on their behalfe into <hi>England,</hi> that they might be remembred in point of Exchanges, and afterwards had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd himſelf in ſome thouſands of crowns, that he the ſaid <hi>Seaman</hi> &amp; others ſhould render themſelves true Priſoners in <hi>Holland.</hi> I ſay, when that Gentleman came to viſitehim, after many acts of Civility ſhewed to him (as if he had received a Penſion from the <hi>Dutch</hi>) he would have knock'd out his brains with ſtones he heav'd at him, ſince he was the State of <hi>Englands</hi> Publick Miniſter, &amp; a man of ſuch worth, as if this inſolent malicious mans conſcience would but ſpeak out, it muſt needs confeſſe; That although the State may have ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny faithfull Servants, it's impoſſible they ſhould have any
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:151526:6"/>in ſuch an employment (as he is in) more ſtudious and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious to promote their Honour and Intereſt.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Richard Badiley.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Here followeth an Anſwer to C. <hi>Ell's</hi> Declaration.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, he ſaith, that ſoone after Capt. <hi>Appletons</hi> Squadron came out of the Mould, the <hi>Dutch</hi> tack'd on them, and then Cap. <hi>Badileys</hi> Squadron might have come at them.</p>
               <p>I have not the ſpirit of Divination, to know what he meanes by that Paſſage: It's truth, we might have come at them, and we did come at them at laſt: but if his meaning be, we might have come at them ſooner then we did; Then thus; As ſoone as ever I ſaw our Ships coming out of the <hi>Mould,</hi> and what the Flemings were minded to doe, I ſent Cap. <hi>Mings</hi> on bord the Frigots, to order the Commanders of them to haſten in with all the Saile they could pack to the aſſiſtance of that Squadron; and he being of the Reer-Admirals Squadron, the <hi>Phoenix</hi> wearing that Flagge, he ought to have followed her with all the Sail he could make; but if he neglected the doing of his Duty, I believe it is not yet too late to call him to accompt, and do juſtice on him for ſuch an Omiſſion.</p>
               <p>If he meanes, I neglected, or loſt time, or did not haſten in as the winde gave leave. I have ſhewed the contrary to that by the Atteſtation of at leaſt halfe a ſcore of very ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Officers, as <hi>Captaines, Lieutenants, Maſters,</hi> and <hi>Maſters-Mates;</hi> and I ſuppoſe it will not be very difficult, now the Fleet's come in, to finde ten ſcore Witneſſes to prove, that I could do no more then I did in haſtning in, if it had been to ſave the Common-wealth.</p>
               <p>In the next place he tells us two of the Enemies ſhips were
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:151526:6"/>on bord the <hi>Leopard</hi> on the Larboard ſide, and they all three lay with their heads to the Weſt-ward.</p>
               <p>This paſſeth as ſmoothly with them that knows not <hi>Star-board</hi> from <hi>Port,</hi> as that paſſage in Cap. <hi>Appletons</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance; wherein he expreſſeth, that when there was no Wind at all, he towed the <hi>Leopard</hi> through the Dutch Fleet, yea, and he towed her againe through them, at which we need not ſay to all Sea-men, pray laugh (ſince he had no help, but of two ſmall Boats) for all ſuch men know that a Land Commander might have been as ſoon believed in ſaying, A Mouſe with a ſtring in my Noſe led me and my Troop through a Regiment of the <hi>Dutch;</hi> and ſo valorous it made us, that it pul'd us through them againe: For thoſe <hi>Dutch</hi> Ships Stemmes and Bow-ſprits lay directly over the <hi>Leopards</hi> Broad-ſide, and conſequently their heads could not lie all one way; the <hi>Leopards</hi> head lay to the South-ward, and the <hi>Flemings</hi> heads lay over her broad ſide to the Weſt-ward, and ſo with their two Top-ſails and fore-ſails they kept full before the Wind, and pog'd her directly towards the ſand that lyeth from the <hi>Malora</hi> all along to the Main.</p>
               <p>And although I am ready to teare my paper, and throw all away, rather then ſpend my time in anſwering ſuch hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid lies, as all theſe <hi>Declarations</hi> are ſtuft withall, yet I ſee there is a neceſſity of my Patience in proceeding.</p>
               <p>He ſaith in the next place, that all my Squadron was to Wind-ward, and ſhot at a great diſtance; but ſome went neerer, as himſelfe for one: Oh valorous man! Whilſt he was at <hi>Civita Vechia,</hi> a moneth or two before he had the States Comimſſion; for then according to what the Boate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwains Mate of the <hi>Hector</hi> (that was in the Ship with him) is ready to make Oath, he out-paſs'd all others, for he drank the Confuſion of the State of <hi>England</hi> (ſaith he) with ſuch heartineſſe, that he heav'd his Hat over-board, and would not let them fetch it againe, being on ſuch a ſcore But it's prov'd by ſundry Witneſſes (and if occaſion be, it will be prov'd by the Oaths of tenne times as many knowing men, who obſerv'd what paſs'd) that thoſe who did leaſt ſervice
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:151526:7"/>among all the Ships, did as much as the <hi>Lewis,</hi> and as I have denoted elſe-where: But for not going on bord the <hi>Leopard,</hi> or coming neer me when our ſhip would not worke, that I might have commanded him to goe upon that ſervice, his Cowardize or negligence therein, muſt needs have cauſed him to be brought under a moſt ſevere ſentence, and if I had brought him home in chaines to have been tryed for his life, for that and other miſdemeanors, all knowing men muſt confeſſe I had done but Juſtice: however if lenity have im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boldned him to be ſo audacious, I ſuppoſe it is not yet too late for authority to call him to an account, and perform that part that I omitted.</p>
               <p>But he proceeds, and tels us, that when he was getting the wind of the <hi>Leopard,</hi> although he had a mans head ſhot off, and another ſhot through the back, and ſome wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, he was intended to relieve the afore-mentioned Ship; but when I ſaw him leane to <hi>Lea-ward,</hi> then I cal'd him after mee.</p>
               <p>This is a pretty ſtory to come from a Saylor in Breeches; I hope his mans head that was ſhot off did not make his ſhip lean to <hi>Lee-ward?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer; when I ſaw that he and others who were neere the <hi>Leopard</hi> (being nimble ſhips) did not execute my or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in going on bord to relieve her, when our Ship the <hi>Parragon</hi> would not beare up to doe it, if it were to ſave a Nation, as it's proved upon oath by ſundry witneſſes, and can be proved by as many ſcore if occaſion require. Yet af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, when about a dozen of my chief Officers (I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe as able men as any were in the Fleet) gave me in their opinion, as they would anſwer it upon their lives, it was no way likely, ſince the <hi>Leopard</hi> was drove ſo neer the ſand, that we could diſ-intangle her from the other ſhips untill all of us were aground, or be deſtroy'd together, I did with-draw, and call off the Squadron: and I had been wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the repute of a mad-man, if I had not done it as I did, all things conſidered.</p>
               <p>I follows next, <hi>That having the Fireſhip neere me, I might have engaged the Dutch Admirall.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:151526:7"/>
               <p> Let all men judge, whether this be not an impudent, brazen-fac'd perſon; and whether hee were not under Hatches, whereas hee ſhould have been looking abroad, when about two hundred and fifty men and boyes that were in the <hi>Parragon</hi> can, and I am confident will (when ever they are call'd to it) make oath that we did engage the Dutch Admirall within Musket-ſhot, and there diſcharg'd a volley of ſmall ſhot, and about 30. piece of Ordnance into him at no further diſtance, leaving him by the Lee: And had we grappl'd, how could the Fireſhip have done her ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution which I order'd her to doe, and yet have ſav'd our owne ſhip; and if an honeſt ſtout perſon had been there to have made all the ſaile hee could for the effecting thereof: But ſuch a bundle of words, and good for little elſe, a proud, prating Conſort (like unto them that put out theſe <hi>Declarations</hi>) I believe the Dutch Admirall might have been fired, and the day have been turn'd by it.</p>
               <p>In the laſt place he ſaith, <hi>The winde was at S. S. E. all day, and with nine ſhips I ſteer'd away, although was chas'd but with eight, and if we had tackt, it would have given a good wipe to our cowardize</hi> (including my ſelfe and all others with the cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardly K. himſelfe) he having received the moſt damage, and that he ſaw the <hi>Leopards</hi> Flag foure hours after he came out. All theſe are ſuch a company of long— that deſerves neither time, nor paper to be ſpent in anſwering them: <hi>Patience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Whereas he ſaith, <hi>he received greater damage then the reſt,</hi> I think his conſort <hi>Fiſher</hi> will quarrell with him about that point: But although the <hi>Parragon</hi> and others might receive three times as many ſhot as he, &amp; loſt men as well as he; if ſhe and others had receiv'd a thouſand great ſhot in the Hull, Maſts, Sailes, and Rigging (as the <hi>Parragon</hi> received little leſſe not many moneths before) and although ¾ of the men were loſt, yet the Commander ought to follow the ſervice they were upon, ſo long as there was any hopes; and if this had been conſidered by him, he would not now bring in a lame excuſe about his damage, in hopes to acquit himſelfe from what he deſerves, in not complying with the Order he
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:151526:8"/>received at the Councell of Warre the day before, which was; <hi>That when the Commander in Chiefe of any ſquadron was removed, thoſe of that ſquadron ſhould attend the Commands of the Admirall; and the Rear-Admirall being aground, he ſhould have attended neer me to know on what ſervice I would have put him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Whereas he ſaith, the wind was at S.S. E. when I cal'd off the Squadron; Becauſe I find him before mentioning his Journall (as now hee doth in the Cloſe) I thought him a greater Proficient in the Art of Navigation (then thoſe that have judg'd he could not ſay his Compaſs) but now it doth not appear.</p>
               <p>For divers underſtanding Seamen have made oath, the wind was about the E. S. E. moſt part of the day, and my ſelfe, and hundreds beſides can freeely make oath, the ſhip lay South, and from the S. by E. to the S. and by W. with the Stem, when we left <hi>Legorn-Road,</hi> and all the Afternoone after, untill we bore away Laskin, ſo that we weather'd the <hi>Gorgana</hi> about 3 or 4 Leagues, and then let all Seamen judge where the wind was.</p>
               <p>And whereas he ſaith, <hi>When but eight Dutch ſhips came af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter us nine, I would not tacke upon them to wipe away our Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardize:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What if but two Frigots of the <hi>Dutch</hi> had followed us, (the reſt being under the ſhoar ready to come off to them) would it have been any wiſdome to have tack'd upon them, ſince the <hi>Parragon</hi> was a foul ſhip that had been off the ground about two years, and all the <hi>Dutch</hi> cleane ſhips? the neereſt was three leagues aſtern from the time they firſt ſtood after us: And pray mark the diſproportionableneſſe that was between us, and you will give ſome eſtimate at the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice that is in this mans heart.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Dutch</hi> were 26 Sail in the morning when they weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but by a hand of God we were reduc'd to nine, at with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing, and we ſaw no damage any of them had receiv'd, except one ſhip ſunck, and their Fireſhip burnt, for which they had taken two of ours, and it may be the Tiller of the Admirals Rudder ſhot in pieces, which could not be long a mending, and one of thoſe on bord the <hi>Leopard</hi> was ready
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:151526:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>to ſinke as we thought, ſo that however they were three to one: But beſides, there was the Reer-Admiralls Squadron, ſixe great Ships, from 46. to 30. piece of Ordnance expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Enemies aſſiſtance from <hi>Meſſina</hi> every moment, and there was a great ſhip look'd for from the Weſt-ward, with 60. piece of Ordnance, and 3 or 400. men, which had in her Ammunition, and all manner of Accoutrements for that Fleet, &amp; two other great ſhips from <hi>Tolloon,</hi> all w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> ſhips arrived next day, or within 2 or 3 days after as I have heard, but none could be expected to our relief. Beſides, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander of the <hi>Conſtant Warwick</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> told me their Main-maſts were ſo cut with ſhot from the Enemie, that they were fearfull they would fall by the bord, ere they could fiſh them ſo, as to ſtrengthen them to carry their ſhips through the Sea. The Commander of the <hi>Phoenix</hi> told me his fore-yard was in pieces, &amp; he muſt have a little time to mend that ere he could do ſervice: The little truſt to be given the greateſt part of my owne Company may be gueſſed at, by the trick they ſerv'd me at my firſt Engagement, the other four or five Merchants ſhips (all but one) little better mann'd, then if they were to carry Salt, or Corn: So that all things being conſidered, I have cauſe to believe, that there is never an underſtanding man in <hi>England,</hi> but muſt have judg'd (the Enemie being above four to one odds) now whether it had been then any prudence to have engag'd further, I leave it to old Souldiers to judg, who were wont to ſay, <hi>Bring a new or young Souldier into the Field, and when once their back is turn'd upon the Enemie, you ſhall never get him (at that time) to ſtand for doing any conſiderable ſervice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But now, if Cap. <hi>Ell</hi> ſhall yet defend himſelfe but from three or four men as well Arm'd as himſelfe, where there is no Wall, Hedge, or Tree to leane his back againſt, I'le for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give him, and be content to ſit downe under the aſpertion he hath laid upon mee: But if not (although Juſtice ſhall ſleepe) I hope it will be no offence in me to deſire the inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of this perſon in Arragning and Condemning his Commander as a Coward before Tryall (who hath beene known to manage a Diſpute by Sea, before he well knew
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:151526:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>how to tye up his Truſles) may open no gapp for other proud, vapouring Sirs to flye in the face, and beſpatter eminent, and gallant Commanders on whom (in ſome ſenſe) I am not worthy to wait.</p>
               <p>Whereas he ſaith he ſaw the <hi>Leopards</hi> Flag foure hours af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter we came away, &amp; ſhe was ſhooting ſo long. By the oaths of very ſufficient witneſſes (that ſtood and look't on as they were priſoners on bord the <hi>Flemings</hi>) it is proved, we could not be gone little above an houre before the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Colours were downe, and the <hi>Dutch</hi> Colours were flying upon the aforenamed Ship.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Here followeth an Anſwer to C. <hi>Fiſher's</hi> Declaration.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, hee ſaith, <hi>That word was ſent from me that very mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning before they came out of the Mould, that I would not have Captaine</hi> Appleton <hi>come forth untill I came neere the Lant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If that be granted, then what madde men were they to come forth before my ſelfe, and the Frigots came there to receive them; or at leaſt before they ſaw me engag'd with the Enemie, ſince it was contrary to their deliberate Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of War that morning, when as Mr. <hi>Longland</hi> was among them, and adviſeth as much by ſeverall Letters.</p>
               <p>Secondly, he ſaith, <hi>I ſent two Meſſengers to order their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out, although one was ſent before to order them not to budge; but ſeeing me ſo wavering, they concluded ſo and ſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſee he and others would faine ſtammer out ſomething to excuſe themſelves, although it's not a little troubleſome to me, I muſt comply with part of ſolemn Councell, by anſwering ſome perſons according to their folly, leſt they be not only wiſe in their own Conceits, but judg'd by other ſo honeſt, as to ſpeak ſomething of truth.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:151526:9"/>
               <p> Firſt then, that men may judge whether I was wavering or no: The 3, or 13. at four a Clock in the morning, I ſent my Feluca in with a Letter to Cap. <hi>Appleton,</hi> the Contents of which was to this effect: <hi>Your ſquadron being the leaſt, I am loath to hazard it, and therefore I would not have you ſtirre before I come cloſe on bord the Mould-head to receive you, or be engaged with the Dutch.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His Anſwer at foure a Clock in the afternonn runs thus; <hi>I thankefully acknowledge your care of this ſquadrons preſervation, but if wee have a fine gale of winde off ſhoar in the night (with your approbation) I will come out.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the beginning of that night, that thoſe in the Mou'd might not be terrified about thoughts of the enemies Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, Cap. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pcher</hi> &amp; <hi>Whiting</hi> went in while it was calm, to tell them they were order'd to attend within Musket-ſhot of the Mould-head in the morning, and that the later was man'd for a Man of War, as well as a Fire-ſhip, to the end ſhe might clap the Enemies Fire-ſhip abord, and ſurprize her in the firſt of our Diſpute, in which ſervice the <hi>Conſtant Warwick</hi> was to attend her.</p>
               <p>About mid-night, ſeeing a moſt gallant freſh gale of wind off ſhore all Eaſterly, I cal'd my Lieut. to me ſaying, take the Feluca, and goe with all ſpeed on bord C. <hi>Appleton,</hi> and tel him, although I ſhal not ſend a warrant poſitively to require him to com away at this inſtant, becauſe I know not how the wind may ſhift before you come there; yet if the gale conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues, let him know I effectually recommend it to him, to cut his Faſts, and come away: He went accordingly to that Squadron, &amp; then I ſuppos'd my ſelf by the light of the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorn (if I were not miſtaken) to be about 3 or 4 miles off in the fair way. It ſeems my Lieut. arrived on bord the <hi>Leopard</hi> about two a Clock the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> in the morning, and having de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered his Meſſage, all the Commanders were cal'd to come and conſult with Cap. <hi>Appleton</hi> what was beſt to be done; the word was paſs'd from ſhip to ſhip, to the Commanders of the <hi>Sampſon, Perigrine,</hi> and <hi>Levant Merchant,</hi> they came: But although they cal'd divers times, Ho the <hi>Mary,</hi> ho the <hi>Mary,</hi> the Admirall hath ſent for us to come away; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:151526:10"/>the Vice-Admirall deſires the Captaine of that ſhip to come and conſult with them about the Buſineſſe, or words to that purpoſe. But the Gentleman could not be made wake in neer two hours after, which is not to be admired at (by thoſe who know what diſeaſe he is troubled with all) In the meane time (while he was abſent) the reſt had ſhewed enough of their waveringneſſe.</p>
               <p>Sometimes the greateſt part of them agreed upon cutting and breaking looſe to go out; but then one more, a Drone, and duller then the reſt, he puts in his verdict to ſtop their intention, ſo that all was laid by before this <hi>Fiſher</hi> came, which made the Maſters Mate of the <hi>Leopard,</hi> one Maſter <hi>Wrightington</hi> ſay in a paſſion, <hi>The Captains were curſed people, and bewitched to that Mould; Why could they not goe out with that gallant freſh gale of winde, now that their Admirall ſent for them?</hi> And I dare preſume, never did men loſe a fairer opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: For as if God had reach'd out a hand from heaven, and pointed it out to them, the Eclipſe of the Moon was juſt at that time: But ſaith he the Flemings were in a Half-moon within Musket-ſhot of the Mould-head with their topſaile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheats hawl'd home, and moſt of their Fore-ſails in the Brailes.</p>
               <p>My Lieutenant that went in with the Feluca, and ſaw all the <hi>Dutch</hi> ſhips how they lay, makes Oath that he ſaw them all very plain by Moone-light, and could not perceive that any one of them had the leaſt part of a ſaile looſe; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, he makes oath, that by his beſt judgment, none could be nearer then about 2 mile off the <hi>Mould-head,</hi> with the ſhips heads that way, directly to Lee-ward of the <hi>Mould,</hi> as much in a Halfe-ſquare as a Halfe-moon for ought he could ſee. Now let all men chuſe whom they will believe, a perſon that was in a Boat neer them, or a perſon that lay faſt aſleep and could not be awak'd by any means.</p>
               <p>The next thing he ſaith, is, <hi>That they expected me neere the Lanthorne when it was day, yet then I was as farre diſtant as over night; and by ſome of our owne Squadrons relation, we lay muzled four Glaſſes, when we might have been by this ſhoar in the morning, and ſo have ſav'd their ſquadron,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:151526:10"/>
               <p> For Anſwer; when as I expected them out, we did lye muzled with lights fore, and aft, and all men ready by the Ordnance to which they were aſſign'd; that if any had eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted them in their way coming out, we would have fill'd our ſailes, and ſtood in to have engag'd them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Now the Reaſons for lying ſhort with our Saile are chiefly theſe.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, in regard we ſaw not the <hi>Malora</hi> before night, and that we might bee miſtaken by taking a light on the Hills for the light of the Lanthorn as ſome have done, and have run aſhore in the night (as I have heard) by that meanes, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſo might we, by labouring to get into <hi>Legorn-Road</hi> at that time with ſuch a Ship of Charge as the <hi>Parragon</hi> is, it being a true ſaying, <hi>Night hath no eyes.</hi> If it be yet replyed, <hi>it was a moone-light night?</hi> I anſwer; When as I have been bound for the above-mentioned Road, even in a Moon-light night in company of C. <hi>Moyer,</hi> and others, that had I believe as able men on bord as any was in our Fleet; and yet in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard we ſaw not the <hi>Malora</hi> before night, although the ſhips in point of Charge were no way proportionable to the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragon,</hi> yet we durſt not venture into that Road, but have layn ſhort all night about the <hi>Gorgona,</hi> untill day-light ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared. Beſides, all the latter part of the night we had an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſe of the Moon that made it wondrous dark, that wee could not diſcern the ſhoar, but they in the Mould might have come off the ſhoar at their pleaſure; and the darker it was, the more for their advantage.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> As I alwayes judg'd it a moſt dangerous thing to engage with ſuch Ships of Charge as we had, in <hi>Legorne</hi> Road, ſo I had ſpent ſundry hours in hammering out a way to draw our Enemies from thence to fight us in the Sea, by ſending Propoſitions as I did to the Great Duke, and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; and I could not imagine, but that the above-named Prince would endeavour to open a doore or paſſage for thoſe Ships in <hi>Legorn</hi>-mould (he commanded forth) to goe out of the reach of his cannons before the <hi>Dutch</hi> ſhould have had the liberty to aſſault them: and conſequently they muſt have come out, if they had an intent to fight us; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:151526:11"/>I judg'd my ſelfe as well to paſſe without the <hi>Malora,</hi> as within, when day light appeared.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> I could not imagine our Ships in the Mould would have come out in the morning before I was engag'd, becauſe they had the Copy of our Orders agreed on at a Councell of Warre the firſt of <hi>March,</hi> wherein they might ſee it was reſolved, that when we came neer <hi>Legorn,</hi> and the winde Eaſterly, we ſhould then make a bord off, by ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a little to the South-ward, purpoſely to tole or entice the Enemie out, that if it were poſſible, our engagement might be without, and not within the <hi>Malora.</hi> And accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to what was endeavoured to bring about, and have effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted for our advantage, it pleaſed God to put into the hearts of the <hi>Dutch</hi> to come out upon us: And when the head-moſt of them were bearing with us, and that we laid our ſhips head to the Offing, diſtant from the <hi>Malora,</hi> as is before ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt, I appeal to all underſtanding Seamen that know that place, whether we had not been as gallantly to paſſe as any men in the world could be, in regard that when the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my had bore to Lee-ward whereby to engage us, they could not have tack'd back upon our friends in the Mould, but in all probability wee might have had the advantage of the winde to have gone backe as faſt as they, thereby to have met that Squadron: But now they imprudently come out before the Enemie was come to Lee-ward upon us, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd us, contrary to reaſon, and my Advice given them in my Letter, dated the day before at four a Clock in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, contrary to their owne deliberate Conſultation, while Mr. <hi>Longland</hi> was with them that morning, whereby they loſt ſuch a ſecond Advantage, which can be far more eaſier diſcern'd, then it was felt, by many that loſt their lives, or were wounded in Body, Eſtate, Reputation, and Peace, which otherwiſe they might have enjoyed, had it not been for that omiſſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Could I have imagin'd they would have come out ſo indiſcreetly, ſince (as they acknowledg) they were advis'd that the <hi>Conſtant Warwick,</hi> and our <hi>Fireſhip</hi> ſhould
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:151526:11"/>be at the <hi>Mould</hi>-head to receive them before they came out.</p>
               <p>But to proceed a little further; <hi>Fiſher</hi> ſaith, <hi>when hee was neere me, he brought his ſhip to the other tacke, and went firing into the Fleet before me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Were we not then at a fine paſſe, that a Gallant, who was the other day a Maſters Mate in a fourth rate ſhip, ſhould as ſoon as he takes Command, preſume to turn Leader to his Admirall? But here he tells a ſtory, that all men amongſt us muſt needs acknowledg to be a miracle: If he bore in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong a Fleet of ſhips, they were inviſible to us; for there was only two of the Enemies on bord the <hi>Leopard,</hi> and the <hi>Dutch</hi> Admirall that was bearing away to the North-ward, all the reſt of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Fleet were to Lee-ward of the <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> then burning, and I do verily believe the aforeſaid Fleet was without ſhot of him, when as he came by the <hi>Julius Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſars</hi> ſtern, as other men did, diſcharging ſome Guns upon her.</p>
               <p>Yet it was not a greater miracle then was told me con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning him in the <hi>Downes,</hi> when as there was a Mutinie on bord the <hi>Mary,</hi> ſome of that Ships Company told me, the Cap. was ſuch a ſottiſh perſon the men could not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to remain under his Command, I replyed, how is this? what is the Captain ſuch a Sot, as that the ordinary Marriners cannot live with him? this is a miracle indeed?</p>
               <p>But whereas this <hi>Fiſher</hi> was ſo valarous as to turn Leader to me; what can he ſay for himſelfe, in that he was back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to doe his duty in the time of the Engagement, which the Laws Martiall ſaith is death. Now for to take away all Excuſes, I ſent him a Copie of theſe Orders that was agreed on at a Councell of War the day before, wherein it was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, that if any Ship of the Admirals, Vice-Admiral, or Reer-Admirals Squadron were laid on bord, the others of that Squadron that were neareſt to ſuch an one, ſhould im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately lay the Enemie on bord againe on the other ſide; or how hee could, that had borded his friend of the ſame Squadron.</p>
               <p>But this <hi>Fiſher,</hi> notwithſtanding he had a nimble cleane
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:151526:12"/>ſhip, and had not loſt above a man or two in coming out: and although he ſaw (or might have ſeen) the <hi>Parragon</hi> would not bear up to goe on bord thoſe ſhips that lay on bord the <hi>Leopard,</hi> had it been to have ſav'd a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth: And howbeit he was one of the Vice-Admirals Squadron, he went not on bord to ſave her, contrary to the expreſſe rule given him for his better government.</p>
               <p>The next thing that concerns me to anſwer (that is not ſufficiently anſwered before;) He ſaith in his opinion, had I ſtood in againe, then I had ſav'd the <hi>Leopard, Perigreen,</hi> and <hi>Levant Merchant,</hi> which I left in a ſad condition.</p>
               <p>Where this malicions mans eyes were I cannot tell, but there are divers men that can make Oath, as ſome men have done already, that the <hi>Perrigreen</hi> was ſurrendred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I cam in ſo farre as to diſcharge my firſt Broad-ſide on thoſe two ſhips on bord the <hi>Leopard,</hi> which the Cap. of her was throughly ſenſible of; and therefore at his going out of the world, declar'd to Mr. <hi>Longland,</hi> and another Witneſſe, who hath now made oath thereof, they could not now blame me in any thing; and added, for not having reſpect to order, their loſſe was brought about, <hi>Oh their deſtruction was of themſelves, their deſtruction was of themſelves,</hi> or words to that purpoſe. And as for the <hi>Levant</hi> Merchant, ſhe was ſurrendred (as we thought) by that time I got firſt in, for the Guns ceaſed between her and the Flemings on bord her: and if any of the <hi>Perrigreens</hi> men be queſtion'd with it, they will tell tell you that it was noys'd fore, and aft their Ship, that the <hi>Levant Merchant</hi> was poſſeſt by the enemie an houre before that ſhip was ſurrendred.</p>
               <p>There is one paſſage more of this vapouring perſon that I am yet to anſwer, and it is this; hee ſaith, <hi>That when he was the ſternmoſt ſhip, I went away with all Saile:</hi> For reaſons before ſignified in my anſwer to <hi>Seaman</hi> and <hi>Ell's</hi> Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, all hopes being paſt, I did order all Saile to be made, in regard now they might take notice I cal'd them away, and withall that we might weather the Rock of the <hi>Malora,</hi> which was little more then Musket-ſhot from us, and at that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:151526:12"/>time we had no more but four fathom and a half water; but whereas he ſaith, he was left in ſome hazard by reaſon of thoſe of the Enemies ſhips that followed him, ſufficient wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hath, or will make <hi>Affidavit,</hi> that thoſe <hi>Dutch-men</hi> of War that followed us, muſt have run about ſix miles, before they could have come at the <hi>Mary,</hi> if ſhe had been at Anchor, and conſequently he could be in no danger; but although I ſuppos'd ſhe could fetch me up when ſhe would, yet being cleare of the <hi>Malora,</hi> I ſhortned ſail (in a ſpecial manner) to know how it was with this Ship, and either ſent a Boat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bord of them, or elſe bid my Lieutenant call to the Cap. on the Poop, and tell him, that although I kept cloſe by a wind while it was day-light, that the enemy might be ſome-what amus'd, and not be able to know which way I determined to goe, either to the Eaſt-ward to meet their <hi>Meſſina</hi> Fleet, or to the Weſt-ward, to hunt after their ſhips with Ammu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition and Proviſions which were coming that way; yet af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it was dark, I would ſteer ſuch a courſe, of which there is ſufficient witneſſe upon oath.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Now having done anſwering the Declarations, give mee leave to adde briefly,</head>
               <p>THe Lawes Martiall for keeping good Diſcipline in the Fleet, by it's 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Article, ſaith, Firſt, <hi>It ſhall be death to be backward in doing ſervice in the time of Engagement.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. By it's 13th Article it ſaith, <hi>Whoſoever ſhall utter words of ſedition, or tending to the making a mutiny, ſhall be lyable to a ſentence of death, which needs be underſtood by the ſevereſt puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> Well then, it is be very ſufficiently prov'd, Cap. <hi>Fiſher</hi> was backward in doing his duty in the time of Engagment, in that he was of the Vice-Admirals Squadron, and yet laid not thoſe ſhips on bord that was on bord the <hi>Leopard,</hi> a piece of negligence abſolutely contrary to his duty. Againe, By teſtimony on oath it appeares, that he abſolutely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus'd to render Conformity or Obedience to the command,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:151526:13"/>or warrant I ſent him under my hand in the Bay of <hi>Logo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Further, it doth as clearly appear, that C. <hi>Ell</hi> did diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey my order at <hi>Genoa,</hi> in not going to <hi>Naples,</hi> or <hi>Meſſina,</hi> although he excus'd it by putting it on his men.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is ſufficiently prov'd, that he did not act according to his Duty in time of our engagement, in that he came not, or at leaſt kept not neare me to know my pleaſure, when his Leader, the <hi>Phaenix</hi> Frigot, was aground upon the Rocks.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In that according to the Teſtimony given in on oath, at my firſt departure from <hi>Legorn,</hi> ſeeing me ſhorten ſaile, to ſtay for one of the Frigots, I ſent in to land a man at <hi>Cerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go,</hi> He calls to Cap. <hi>Godolphin,</hi> Commander of the <hi>William,</hi> and <hi>Thomas,</hi> with theſe words in his mouth, <hi>The Admirall looſes time, he hath a minde to</hi> Porto Longone, <hi>or elſe-where untill he ſells us into the hands of the Dutch, they are like to be at the Streights mouth before us, and therefore let us Merchant-men be gone, and leave the Admirall to ſhift for himſelfe,</hi> or words to that purpoſe. By which it appears, that although (it may be) <hi>Robert Lendall</hi> that ſtir'd up the Mariners to reſiſt the commands of that Gentleman, who was Vice-Admirall in 1648 and ſo to mutiny only on bord that one ſhip, this man would have ſeverall ſhips to commit ſuch unſufferable diſorder.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It's proved by ſufficient Witneſſe upon oath, that the afore-mentioned <hi>Ell</hi> did contemptuouſly contrary to all his friends advice, diſobey my Warrant, and the lawful Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand I ſent him under my hand in the Bay of <hi>Logos.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly, It will appear by witneſſe enough, at our laſt coming into the <hi>Downes,</hi> that although I gave him leave to be wanting from his ſhip about ten hours, he ſtaid above ten dayes, which doubtleſſe occaſioned his men to mutiny as they did, when by Authority they were commanded forth to Sea.</p>
               <p>So that now if the high diſorders and contempts of theſe two men (at leaſt) be adjudg'd of according to our Lawes Martiall, without dipping my pen in Gall, or any kind of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:151526:13"/>paſſion, or bitterneſſe, if I ſhould aske the queſtion of the moſt moderad'ſt man that underſtands any thing of Martiall Diſcipline by Sea or Land, and ſay, Pray what do you think could be done leſſe, in caſe I had been inveſted with the power (that undoubtedly belongs to one in my Command, at ſo great a diſtance) and had diſingag'd perſons about me at their Tryall, then to have given a ſentence of death either at the yard Arme, or elſe how, would it not be anſwered in the Affirmative? And if ſo, here we have the old Proverb as rightly fulfil'd as may be; <hi>Save a Thiefe from the Gallows, and he will hang thee if he can,</hi> theſe men having now ſtruck at my life (as we uſe to ſay) with a witneſſe.</p>
               <p>I have yet one word more; the great <hi>Jehovah</hi> that knows all mens actions, and the end they drive at, at whoſe Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeat we muſt all one day appeare, can witneſſe for me the truth of what I am now about to ſay, which I am alſo ready to make Oath of when ever I am cal'd to it; ſome of theſe perſons that appeare now againſt me in Print, as one that were either a Traitor, a Coward, or at leaſt a negligent perſon in the management of that buſineſſe at <hi>Legorn.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In our home-ward way, ſeeing me walk more reſerv'd, and melancholy (as they thought) then I was uſually wont to doe, they have come to mee with theſe words in their mouths ſundry times, <hi>Good Sir, be not diſcontented, nor melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholly about what hath fallen out, no man in the world could do more then you have done; and had you engag'd further (without all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure) wee had loſt all the Fleet;</hi> or words to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
               <p>Wherefore I thinke, to reaſonable men it muſt needs ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear we have a ſort of naughty malicious people in <hi>England,</hi> that have incited ſome of theſe perſons to what originally they intended not, and conſequently it may ſtir us up to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that the work which (according to the hope of many) hath been upon the wheel for almoſt twice ſeven years, may be carryed on to a greater perfection.</p>
               <p>And I ſuppoſe it may be eaſily gathered from what hath been before denoted, there are a ſort of people that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:151526:14"/>would imitate ſome houſe Carpenters, who being deſirous to make quick work for plucking down a Fabrick erected, firſt endeavoureth to ſtrike away the ſmall Rafters, that at the great Supporters, or Beames, they may fctch a blow (as we uſe to ſay) to the purpoſe.</p>
               <p>In fine, it is well for ſome they have in their hearts a very ready anſwer to that notable queſtion of the Wiſe man:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But who is able to ſtand before envy,</hi> Prov. 27.4.</p>
               <p>For ſome can boldly ſay, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Honours very humble Servant, Rich. Badiley.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:151526:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>Legorn, <date>
                     <hi>Sept. 19. 1653.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>CAPT. BADILEY; <hi>SJR,</hi>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have not had any from you: I was told by ſome of our Nation, that <hi>Appleton</hi> &amp; <hi>Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> play the Divels at home againſt you (in theſe very words) and that they had car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried home many Writings and Certificates a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you; 'tis the firſt word I heard of it, however I believe it may be true; for nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them want malice againſt any that are truly affected to the Common-wealth: they cannot want ſuch here as will give their hands againſt the State themſelves; and I am confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent there is not a man, but ſuch a one, that would ſubſcribe any writing againſt you. I know ſuch were their intimate friends, as day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly drank Healths to the States Confuſion; and if ſuch hands ſhould paſſe againſt their faithfull
<pb facs="tcp:151526:15"/>Servants, I ſhall take my leave of their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. 'Tis a vile diſpoſition in man, that when God ſends Affliction, inſtead of hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling of himſelfe under that hand, he flyes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his fellow-ſervants, and imputes the fault to them; 'Tis juſt the caſe of <hi>Wadſworth,</hi> whoſe Letters writ mee from <hi>Porto Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone,</hi> I herewith ſend you, which you may ſhew to whom it concernes. The <hi>Dutch</hi> are all gone weſtward towards <hi>Cales,</hi> except a Ships, who lye here in Port; they ſay like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe that the Boare is to goe home, when Young <hi>Trump</hi> comes up to him. I reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Servant,</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <p>
               <hi>Although I never thought to come in Print againe, a few weeks ſince; yet being conſtrained to it at this time, receiving this Letter by the French Post, juſt upon fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing, I have thought fit to inſert it; and if any doubt of the truth of it, I ſhall not onely ſhew the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, but make Oath it came unexpectedly to my hand, this</hi> 3 <hi>of Octob.</hi> 1653.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Ri: Badiley.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
